<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
     xmlns:fx="http://pipoptagada"
     type=""
     n="">Protocol on the Interpretation of <ref type="article" n="69">Article 69</ref> EPC
                <argument>
      <p>
                      of 5 October 1973  
                    
                      as revised by the Act revising the EPC of 29 November 2000<note n="f1">
                  The new text of the Protocol adopted by the Administrative
                  Council of the European Patent Organisation in its decision of
                  28 June 2001 (see OJ EPO 2001, Special edition No. 4, p. 55)
                  has become an integral part of the Revision Act of 29 November
                  2000 under Article 3(2), second sentence, of that Act.
                </note>
      </p>
   </argument>
   <head>Article 1</head>
   <argument>
      <p>General principles
                </p>
   </argument>
   <div type="paragraph">
      <p>
         <ref type="article" n="69">Article 69</ref> should not be interpreted
                  as meaning that the extent of the protection conferred by a
                  European patent is to be understood as that defined by the
                  strict, literal meaning of the wording used in the claims, the
                  description and drawings being employed only for the purpose
                  of resolving an ambiguity found in the claims. Nor should it
                  be taken to mean that the claims serve only as a guideline and
                  that the actual protection conferred may extend to what, from
                  a consideration of the description and drawings by a person
                  skilled in the art, the patent proprietor has contemplated. On
                  the contrary, it is to be interpreted as defining a position
                  between these extremes which combines a fair protection for
                  the patent proprietor with a reasonable degree of legal
                  certainty for third parties.
                </p>
   </div>
   <head>Article 2</head>
   <argument>
      <p>Equivalents
                </p>
   </argument>
   <div type="paragraph">
      <p>
                  For the purpose of determining the extent of protection
                  conferred by a European patent, due account shall be taken of
                  any element which is equivalent to an element specified in the
                  claims. 
                </p>
   </div>
</div>
